Finding Aid for Guild House records 1924-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Guild House records 1924-2005 1940-1990
Guild House (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Ecumenical Christian campus ministry at the University of Michigan. Records include correspondence, minutes, financial reports, annual reports, newsletters, photographs, audio-tapes; materials concerning University of Michigan religious organizations, including Office of Religious Affairs, the Association of Religious Counselors, Student Religious Association, the Interfaith Center, and the Protestant Foundation for International Students; also files on other religious organizations, especially the Ann Arbor Bible Chair, the Michigan Christian Foundation of the Disciples of Christ; and papers concerning Ann Arbor churches, particularly the Bethlehem Evangelical Church, the First Congregational Church, and the Memorial Christian Church.
8514 Ba 2
10 linear feet
6 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were received from the Guild House (Donor No. 5848 ) beginning in 1976; periodic additions have been received since then.
The records are open for research.
The roots of Guild House go back to 1893 when the Christian Women's Board of Missions of the Disciples Church established the Ann Arbor Bible Chair at the University of Michigan. Through the years other denominations have joined the Disciples in their aim to provide a setting for Bible study and the "Christian education" of university students. The Guild House became an ecumenical "United Campus Ministry" with local churches sponsoring their activities. These included Memorial Christian Church, the Bethlehem United Church of Christ, the First Congregational Church, the Church of the Good Shepherd, and the First Unitarian Universalist Church.
The historical development of the modern Guild House has many strains. One of these certainly was the Disciples' missionary outreach to the university community. Also significant was the appointment in 1934 of H. L. Pickerill as director of student work for the Michigan Christian Foundation (Disciples of Christ). In this capacity, Pickerill subsequently organized the Disciples Guild, which was the immediate forerunner of the modern Guild House. During the war, there was a move to bring together some of the other denominational groups sharing similar goals respecting the university student community. In 1942, the Disciples of Christ and the Congregational Church agreed to cooperate in this ministry, forming the Congregational and Disciples Guild. Then in 1958, following the merger of the Congregational Church and the Evangelical and Reformed Church into the United Church of Christ, the local groups formally incorporated as the Congregational and Christian Parish House, or Guild House as it came to be called. In 1969, a decade later, the name of the organization was officially changed to Guild House to reflect its character an ecumenical organization with the inclusion of additional denominational sponsorship.
Through the years, Guild House has provided a supportive environment for campus groups to debate and exchange ideas. Social issues of concern included in the 1970s, 80s, and 90s included U.S.-Latin American foreign policy, Recombinant DNA, issues of sexuality and the role of men and women in the church, and cases of sexist and racist discrimination at the University of Michigan. Guild House has worked to foster an atmosphere of creativity, spiritual growth, and sharing of ideas. The House offered weekly poetry readings and "Great Awakening" discussion groups, as well as fund raising dinners to support self-help and self-development groups in Central America. In 2000s, Guild House began and annual Alternative Spring Break trip to Honduras. The Guild House also provided counseling for students and faculty having problems on matters of religious belief and concerns about social and personal matters.
Some time in the 2000s the Board of Guild House "determined that the students of the University of Michigan require a different approach to their search for religious truth."1 This brought an end to the over 100-year ministry of Guild House. Currently the Board of Trustees is determining what new form of ministry should emerge to replace Guild House.
The records of Guild House have come to the library in different accessions dating from the 1970s. Covering the period from the 1920s to the 2000s, the records document the different roots of the modern Guild House. Besides correspondence, financial reports and annual reports, the record group includes the student newsletter The Microphone, as well as various reports of retreats, banquets, luncheons, and discussion sessions.
Because the members of the Guild House were so active, the record group includes materials on social issues such as civil rights, disarmament, diplomatic recognition of China, apartheid, and social and political issues in Central America. For a view of the Vietnam War peace movement and other political issues the collection of J. Edgar Edwards, director and campus minister of the Guild House from 1957 to 1973, should be consulted. This collection has been separately cataloged.
There are also numerous sound tape recordings of Guild House programs and meetings, a microfilm copy of the record book of the Upper Room membership under H.L. Pickerill's predecessor Thomas Iden, photographs, and scrapbooks.
More specifically, the record group has been arranged into the following series: Church Campus Ministries; Guild House Organizational Records; Related Organizations; Publications and related; Directors; Photographs, Scrapbooks, and Sound Recordings. The strength of the collection is its documentation of Guild House's involvement in significant social and political issues of the 1950s-2000s.
Subjects:
Bethlehem United Church of Christ (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor Bible Chairs.; First Congregational Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Guild House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Memorial Christian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Congregational churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Disciples of Christ--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Memorial Christian Foundation.; Evangelical Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Association of Religious Counselors (University of Michigan); Interfaith Center (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Office of Religious Affairs.; Protestant Foundation for International Students (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Religion.; University of Michigan. Student Religious Association.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Edwards, J. Edgar (Joseph Edgar), 1909-1973.; Guild House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Demonstrations.
Subjects - Audio-Visual Material
Guild House (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre/Form:
CD-ROMs.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.
- Church Campus Ministries
  The first series Church Campus Ministries documents the various Christian student groups that have been associated with and became a part of Guild House in the twentieth century. These records include administrative records, correspondence, newsletters, and reports on the merger of student groups with Guild House.
  - First Congregational Church of Ann Arbor and its campus ministry
    - Papers 1942-1946 (Box 1)
    - Papers 1949-1958 (Box 1)
  - Congregational Christian Church of Ann Arbor and its campus ministry
    - Papers 1943-1956 (Box 1)
  - Evangelical and Reformed Church
    - Student Guild 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - Christian Student Foundation (MSU)
    - Newsletters 1957 (Box 1)
  - Disciples of Christ
    - Campus ministry undated (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Bible Chair
      - Papers 1924-1933 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1933-1936 (Box 1)
      - Iden Trust Fund 1942-1951 (Box 1)
      - Background for Bible Chair study 1954 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous lists undated (Box 1)
      - Biographical sketch of Dr. Clinton Lockhart 1944 (Box 1)
    - Reports on student work 1935-1955 (Box 1)
    - United Missionary Society, Student Center reports 1950-1958 (Box 1)
    - Vacation church schools 1934-1940 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Christian Foundation
      - Constitution 1934 (Box 1)
      - Minutes 1924-1950 (Box 1)
      - Officers 1940-1945 (Box 1)
      - Board members undated, 1938-1948 (Box 1)
      - Reports to Disciples of Christ 1948-1955 (Box 1)
      - Finance 1943-1957 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Student Christian Movement convocation 1950 (Box 1)
      - Psychological factors in the relation between pastor and student worker 1953 (by H.L. Pickerell) (Box 1)
  - United Church of Christ
    - Merger papers 1956-1957 leading to establishment of GH (Box 1)
  - Student Christian movements
    - Merger reports 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Fellowship of Campus Ministers
    - Minutes 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - Upper Room
    - Membership Records, 1 microfilm roll separately located (Reel 1)
- Guild House Organizational Records
  Guild House Organizational Records, the second series, documents the history of Guild House as an organization from 1938-2000. Records in this series include administrative and financial record, public relations materials, membership records, and records related to activities and programs sponsored by Guild House.
  - Articles of Incorporation, Bylaws, and Mission Statement 1969, 1989, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (H.L. Pickerill) undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1941-1966, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual Report 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Banquets
    - Banquets 1953-1959 (Box 1)
    - Alumni banquet correspondence 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - New Student Banquet 1952-1960 (Box 1)
  - Board Members and Supporters 1984-1995 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Building Future Task Force 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - Building Renovation 1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (related material from 1967)
  - Christmas Programs 1954-1959 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and articles about GH (Box 1)
  - Committees 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Congregational and Disciples Alumni Association 1959-1963 (Box 1)
  - Covenant Community 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - Congregational Student Work, Report on (Box 1)
  - Directors' Personnel files 1975-2001, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Drawing by Milton Kemnitz (Box 1)
  - Elections 1938-1958 (Box 1)
  - Financial materials
    - Finance 1940-1955 (Box 2)
    - Budgets undated, 1945-1966 (Box 2)
    - Budget 1947-1969 (Box 2)
    - Maintenance and building improvements 1945-1946 (Box 2)
    - Special funds 1947-1956 (Box 2)
    - Campus minister's imprest fund 1957-1959 (Box 2)
    - Mortgages 1958-1961 (Box 2)
    - Director's expenses 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    - Treasurer's reports 1958-1963 (Box 2)
    - Cash statement 1959-1966 (Box 2)
    - Fund report 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous accounts 1964 (Box 2)
  - First Unitarian Church Affiliation (Box 2)
  - Freshman discussion group 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - General Descriptions circa 1960s-2000s (Box 2)
  - Graduate student group 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - Guild Council Membership 1946-1958 (Box 2)
  - Guild Council leadership training 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - Guild Council 1950, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Guild House: "The Development of Community in the Late 20th Century," by Gregory K. Nishimura 1997 (Box 2)
  - Honors Dinner 1961 (Box 2)
  - Housing Proposal, draft circa 1969 (Box 2)
  - International Students (Box 2)
  - Issues and Projects
    - Ann Arbor Community self-survey 1956
      - Employment (Box 2)
      - Youth (Box 2)
      - New residents (Box 2)
      - Community and human relations (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor housing and urban renewal 1959 (Box 2)
    - China
      - Diplomatic recognition of China 1959 (Box 2)
      - Conference on U.S.-China relations 1965 (Box 2)
    - Disarmament 1958 (Box 2)
    - Discrimination / Race relations
      - Church statements 1956-1959 (Box 2)
      - Non-violent direct action committee 1960 (Box 2)
      - Clippings 1958-1959 (Box 2)
      - Race Relations at the University of Michigan 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - Foster parent plan 1959 (Box 2)
    - Hungarian student 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Integration 1955-1961 (papers and correspondence), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - International economic and social development 1952 (Box 2)
    - March on Washington 1959 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Membership lists
    - Disciples of Christ student membership 1946-1957 (Box 2)
    - Prospective membership and church preference undated, 1951-1959, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Merger of Campus Ministries 1967-1969 (Box 3)
  - Minutes of various meetings
    - Guild Council minutes Undated, 1941-1966, 19 folders (Box 3)
    - Personnel Committee (minutes) 1962, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Joint staff meeting minutes undated, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - Joint Administrative Board minutes 1958-1969 (Box 3)
    - Administrative Board annual meeting papers 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - Student work committees minutes 1944-1958 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee minutes 1961-1969, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Board of Trustees minutes 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Annual membership board minutes 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Campus ministry minutes 1962-1967 (Box 3)
  - Official Resolutions Honoring Guild House Centennial 1993 (Box 3)
  - Organization 1948-1971 (Box 3)
  - Plan of Ministry circa 1970s (Box 3)
  - Programs and Events
    - Centennial Weekend 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Friday Forums 1976-1988, undated (Box 3)
    - Interfaith Discussions for Undergraduates circa 1990s (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Events 1968-1995 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Noon Flyers 1987, undated (Box 3)
    - Poetry Series Reading Selections 1976 October-1977 March (Box 4)
    - Poetry Series, Noon Luncheon Speakers, and Writers Series, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Program Announcements circa 1964-1969 (Box 4)
    - Program Announcements circa 1974-1990 (Box 4)
    - Program Committee 1947-1950 (Box 4)
    - Program Information and Ads 2000, undated (Box 4)
    - Program Proposals (Box 4)
    - Programs 1952-1972 (Box 4)
    - Second Wednesday Supper Forum undated (Box 4)
    - Special Events 1987, 1991, undated (Box 4)
    - Students Involved for the Global Neighborhood (SIGN) 1994-1995, undated (Box 4)
    - Women and Power Series undated (Box 4)
    - Women and Spirituality Group 1988, undated (Box 4)
    - Writers Series 1988-1999 (Box 4)
  - Program evaluation 1974 of Guild House (Box 4)
  - Purpose (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Reports (various)
    - Campus minister and staff reports undated, 1958-1972 (Box 4)
    - Associates reports 1959-1961 (Box 4)
    - Student Center reports 1959 (Box 4)
    - Staff Reports 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - Resident Guest Program 1963 (Box 4)
  - Retreats
    - Retreat reports undated, 1939-1965 (Box 4)
    - Retreat correspondence 1954-1958 (Box 4)
    - Retreats miscellaneous 1953-1962 (Box 4)
  - Seminars 1946-1965 (Box 4)
  - Sermonettes 1960 (Box 4)
  - Social Action Committee 1958-1959 (Box 4)
  - Student Christian education (papers about) undated, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Summer Program 1953, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - United Church of Christ
    - Lay Life and Work, Commission on 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - Christian Nurture, Division of 1965-1969 (Box 4)
  - University Christian Movement 1965-1967 (Box 4)
  - Worship Services 1954-1963 (Box 4)
- Related Organizations
  The third series, Related Organizations, documents the history of other Christian campus organizations at the University of Michigan. These records are primarily administrative and financial in nature, but also include correspondence, newsletters, news clippings, and records related to campus programming.
  - Association of Religious Counselors
    - Minutes 1956-1961, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Curriculum Committee undated (Box 5)
    - Discussions 1973 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1956-1957 (Box 5)
  - Campus Ministry Women
    - Bylaws (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1976, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Financial Reports 1978 (Box 5)
    - Membership Directory 1979 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters 1978-1981 (Box 5)
  - Campus ministry workshops, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Christian Federation Advisors
    - Minutes 1955-1961, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Retreat 1959 (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea 1956-1957 (Box 5)
  - Christian Student Directors Association 1953-1956 (minutes) (Box 5)
  - Council of Student Religious Organization
    - Minutes undated, 1948-1951 (Box 5)
    - Papers 1957-1964 (Box 5)
  - Covenant Community
    - Lectures undated, 1963 of J. Edgar Edwards (Box 5)
    - Papers 1963-1965 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1966 (Box 5)
  - Danforth Seminary internship undated (Box 5)
  - Ecumenical Campus Ministry
    - Organization 1962-1964 (Box 5)
    - Minutes 1961 (Box 5)
    - Finance 1966 (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea (Box 5)
  - Fellowship of Campus Ministers 1958-1960 (minutes) (Box 5)
  - Interfaith Center
    - Organization (Box 5)
    - Reports undated, 1956-1966 (Box 5)
    - Memos and correspondence 1956-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Minutes 1963-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Finance 1966-1970 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters 1967-1968 (Box 5)
    - Leadership 1967-1969 (Box 5)
    - Clippings (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea undated, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Interguild papers 1954-1956 (Box 5)
  - International Student Association undated (Box 5)
  - Joint Campus Ministry conference 1960-1962 (Box 5)
  - Protestant Foundation for International Students
    - Reports 1957-1960 (Box 5)
    - Minutes 1958-1961 (Box 5)
    - The World on My Doorstep newsletter 1958-1961 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence undated, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Student financial reports 1958-1961 (Box 5)
    - Papers 1960 (Box 5)
  - Student Religious Association
    - Constitution (Box 5)
    - Workbooks 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters 1953-1954 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    - The Year Ahead 1950-1956, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea 1953-1957 (Box 5)
  - World University Service 1956-1957 (Box 6)
  - United Campus Christian Fellowship
    - Constitution (Box 6)
    - Papers 1956-1966 (Box 6)
  - United Campus Ministry 1962-1966 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan Office of Religious Affairs
    - Organization undated, 1956 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1947-1958 (Box 6)
    - Religious census 1920, 1952-1961 (Box 6)
    - Committee on Studies of Religion
      - Correspondence 1964 (Box 6)
      - Reports 1958-1966 (Box 6)
    - Commission on Religion in the Curriculum (minutes) 1964 (Box 6)
    - Radical theology conference 1966 (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook 1957-1958 re religion at the U-M (Box 6)
- Publications and related materials
  Publications and related, the fourth series, documents Guild House's publications and public performances. The series includes newsletters, brochures, calendars, a yearbook, and scripts for plays.
  - Brochure Originals 1989-1991 (Box 6)
  - Calendars 1985-1992 (scattered) (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous plays undated (Box 6)
  - Meditations 1950-1956 published by GH members (Box 6)
  - Microphone Vols. 1-15, 1941-1958 (Box 6)
  - Summer projects newsletter 1954 (Box 6)
  - Alumni newsletters 1938-1975, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Program newsletters 1951-1957 (Box 6)
  - Yearbook undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous: include "An Occasional Newsletter", 2 folders (Box 6)
- Directors
  Directors, the fifth series, documents the role of the men and women who led Guild House in the twentieth century. The series begins with the J. Edgar Edwards files (1960-1974), which contain staff and administrative reports specific to the Edwards directorship, as well as documentation of Edwards's role in the Morton Sobell case. The Don and Ann Marie Coleman files (1975-1991) include administrative, financial, and topic files related to the Colemans' directorship. The Jodi and Christ Atwood files (1991-1997) and the Diane Christopherson files (1997-2001) contain administrative and financial records of their directorships.
  - J. Edgar Edwards files 1960-1974
    - Staff reports (also some speeches and other statements) 1960-1972 (Box 7)
    - Joint Administrative Board (minutes and financial statements) 1965-1973 (Box 7)
    - Edwards memorial fund 1973-1974 (letters received in response to his death and to the establishment of a fund in his honor) (Box 7)
    - Morton Sobell Case 1960, 2 folders (Box 7)
      (collected material dates back to 1953)
    - Vietnam Concerns 1965, undated (Box 7)
  - Don and Ann Marie Coleman files 1975-1991
    - Administrative files
      - Executive Board
        - Executive board members 1988-1989 (Box 7)
        - Executive board notebook (contains mission statement, bylaws, job descriptions, etc.) (Box 7)
        - Staff reports 1973-1974, 1987-1990 (Box 7)
        - Board Minutes 1977-1980 (Box 7)
        - Board Minutes 1982-1985 (Box 7)
        - Board Minutes 1986, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Board Minutes 1987, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Board Minutes 1988, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Board Minutes 1989 (Box 7)
        - Board Minutes 1990 (Box 7)
        - Board miscellaneous 1989-1990 (Box 7)
        - Executive Board Miscellaneous 1980, 1986-1990 (contains meeting minutes, information of staff retreat, etc.) (Box 7)
      - Finance Committee
        - Financial Reports 1975-1990, 5 folders (Box 7)
        - Financial Study 1987 (Box 7)
        - Finance, Miscellaneous 1980-1990 (include financial plans and reports, fundraising ideas, correspondence, etc.) (Box 7)
    - Topical (and other office files)
      - Announcements of programs 1977-1984, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Brochures and brochure design plans undated (Box 7)
      - Campus Ministry Women 1977-1979 (Box 7)
      - Central America contingency plan 1984 (Box 7)
      - Committee on Ministry in Post Secondary Education Request for Funding 1983 (Box 7)
      - Concerned Faculty 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Conscientious objector information 1979, undated (Box 8)
      - Correspondence (of GH office and of the Colemans) 1976-1989, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Early Apartheid Collected Materials 1978-1979 (Box 8)
      - Faculty Committee for Human Rights in El Salvador (FACHRES) 1980-1987 (Box 8)
      - Faculty Group 1978-1982 (Box 8)
      - Great Awakenings 1983-1989, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Guild House stationery design undated (Box 8)
      - Harding, Vincent (speaker at Guild House) 1988 (Box 8)
      - Historical background of Guild House (Box 8)
      - Mailing list November 1989 (Box 8)
      - Men's Support Group 1989 (members list) (Box 8)
      - Newspaper clippings 1976-1992 (Box 8)
      - Newsletter, Spring 1989 (Box 8)
      - PAC (political action committee) 1984 (Box 8)
      - Phone-a-thon 1989 (Box 8)
      - Posters, flyers, etc. (Box 8)
      - Presbytery of Detroit Council Meeting Minutes November 1989-January 1990 (Box 8)
      - Retreat summary 1984 (Box 8)
      - Self study workshop (Box 8)
      - Solidarity Council undated (Box 8)
      - United Church of Christ Board of Directors Meeting Minutes March-April 1980, December 1989-February 1990 (Box 8)
  - Jodi and Chris Atwood files 1991-1996
    - Administrative Files
      - Executive Committee
        - Agendas 1992 (Box 8)
        - Minutes 1991-1996, 5 folders (Box 8)
      - Financial Committee
        - Financial Reports 1991-1996, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Staff Reports 1994-1995 (Box 8)
  - Diane Christopherson files 1997-2003
    - Administrative Files
      - Executive Committee
        - Minutes 1997-1999, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Financial Committee
        - Financial Reports 1997-2003 (Box 8)
- Photographs
  The sixth series, Photographs, visually documents Guild House events and members from the 1950s to 2005. Photographs include people, activities, nature, and buildings.
  - Activities (Box 9)
  - Buildings circa 1950s-1960s (Box 9)
  - Guild House Photograph Album 2001-2002 (Box 9)